Finding Aid for Albert Kahn Family Papers, 1869-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Albert Kahn Family papers 1869-1989
Kahn family.
1 linear foot
0442 Aa/2
The Albert Kahn Family Papers include the personal correspondence of Albert, his wife Ernestine Krolik Kahn, his son Edgar Adolph Kahn, and his daughter Ruth Kahn Rothman, miscellaneous materials which document the personal and professional lives of family members, and photographic images from the 1870s to the late 1980s.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection came from Carol Kahn (Donor No. 9202 ) on 5/15/2002; additional papers came from William R. Brashear (Donor No. 9864 ) in July 2009.
The collection is open for research.
As America's most influential industrial architect, Albert Kahn revolutionized the health and safety conditions of early twentieth-century factories and worked closely with Henry Ford to implement his vision of the assembly line at the Highland Park and River Rouge automobile plants. Kahn pioneered the use of reinforced concrete, non-intrusive steel structures, natural ventilation and glass building skins to respond to the changing functional needs of the American factory. His pragmatism, ability to listen to the needs of the client and experimentation with innovative building technologies resulted in a new industrial architecture, which inspired the development of European Modernism by Walter Gropius, Mies van der Rohe and Le Corbusier. Hugely versatile in his design capabilities and strongly interested in historic architecture, Kahn also produced many commercial and institutional icons in Detroit and at the University of Michigan, including the Fisher Building, Detroit Athletic Club, General Motors Building, Hill Auditorium, Angell Hall, William L. Clements Library and Burton Memorial Carillon Tower. This most prolific of American architects built over 2000 projects in his lifetime, including 521 factories in Russia between 1929 and 1932, and in 1938 was constructing 19% of all architect-designed industrial facilities in the United States. When he died in 1942, he had signed defense contracts totaling $200 million for the construction of the Willow Run Bomber Plant and naval bases in Honolulu, Midway Island, Puerto Rico and Kodak, Alaska, among other war-time facilities.
In 1896, Kahn married Ernestine Krolik, the daughter of Adolph Krolik, who was a successful dry goods merchant and a client of the young architect. A graduate of the University of Michigan in 1892, Ernestine was a talented gardener and interior designer, who often advised Albert on matters of color and fabric selection. When speaking of her parents, their daughter Rosalie Kahn Butzel said years later that "they complemented each other wonderfully."[1] Albert and Ernestine had two other daughters, Lydia and Ruth, and one son, Edgar (1900-1985). "Eddie" became the first scorer and captain of the University of Michigan hockey team, graduating from the University Medical School in 1924. From 1949 to 1971, he served as the Chairman of Neurosurgery at the University of Michigan Hospital (designed by his father in 1919).
For a full history of Albert Kahn's career, please see the finding aid for the Albert Kahn Papers.
___________________
Notes:
[1] Richard Bak, "Blueprint for Detroit," HOUR Detroit (May, 2000, reprinted by Albert Kahn Associates, Inc.), p. 2
The Kahn Family papers have come to the library from two sources: from Carol Kahn, the granddaughter of Albert and Ernestine Kahn, and from William R. Brashear, a biographer of Albert Kahn. The Albert Kahn Family Papers received from Carol Kahn includes letters, miscellaneous materials and photographs which contribute to our understanding of Kahn’s relationship with his wife and children. The materials illuminate the personal side of Kahn’s life and document the distinguished military and professional careers of his son Edgar (1900-1985), who served as Chairman of Neurosurgery at the University of Michigan Hospital from 1949 to 1971. The papers received from William R. Brashear include papers of Ruth Kahn Rothman and Edward E. Rothman.
Subjects:
Kahn family.; Architects--Michigan--Detroit.; Kahn, Albert, 1869-1942.; Kahn, Edgar A.; Kahn, Ernestine Krolik.; Rothman, Ruth Kahn.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Neurosurgery.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. Section of Neurosurgery.; University of Michigan--Hockey.; Kahn, Albert.; Kahn, Edgar A.; Kahn, Ernestine.
Contributors
Peet, Max Minor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Kahn Family papers, Carol Kahn collector
  The Albert Kahn Family Papers received from Carol Kahn encompass three subseries, Correspondence, Miscellaneous Papers and Photographs and Audio-Visual Materials.
  - Correspondence
    The Correspondence subseries includes letters to and from Albert Kahn, his wife Ernestine Krolik Kahn, his son Edgar Adolph Kahn and his granddaughter Carol Kahn. While the letters from Albert number only four, researchers will find his letter to his sister-in-law Amy of 11/9/1900 to be of particular interest. In this hand-written piece of correspondence, Kahn recounts his delight in visiting Paris, Genoa, and Florence in 1891 and includes a sketch of an Italian arch. He also expresses pride and delight in his baby son, Edgar. Two late letters of 6/26/1940 and 7/17/1942 to Edgar, who was posted for military duty in Spain and Little Rock, Arkansas, are also significant. In these documents, Kahn describes his own war defense work and expresses concern for his son's welfare. He gives us a glimpse of paternal emotion when he ends the 1940 letter with these words to Eddie: "You mean everything to all of us." The four letters to Kahn in this series include two from his brother Julius (one dated 1/14/1900), with whom he collaborated on the use of reinforced concrete in structural design. Also included is a letter from his first partner Alexander Buel Trowbridge (10/17/1898), who had recently become the dean of the Cornell University College of Architecture.
    Within the Correspondence subseries, the letters written by Kahn's future wife Ernestine Krolik at the age of 16 give researchers a view of the personality of this intelligent, young woman, who shows herself to be cultured, confident and family-oriented. Twenty-one letters were written by Ernestine during her summer visit in St. Paul, Minnesota from 6/29/1885 to 9/1/1885. They were addressed to her mother, sister Bell, brother Day and father Adolph Krolik, a dry goods merchant who would later become a client of Albert Kahn. In addition to her descriptions of her train trips to such tourist destinations as Lake Johanna, White Bear Lake and Lake St. Croix, she provides detailed walking-tour portraits of the cities of St. Paul and Minneapolis in 1885. Of particular note is Ernestine's letter of 7/25/1885 to her mother, in which she describes her meeting of "a Mr. Kahn," who accompanied her and her German friend Emma to the Tivoli beer garden. Her description of his personal appearance and some of his rather indelicate remarks is hilarious. Her letters show her to have a game sense of adventure, as well as a strong devotion to her parents, whose "kindness and warm-heartedness" she praises. Included in the letters to Ernestine is a 1942 Western Union telegram from V. A. Vernin, Russian Architect-Academician, expressing "sympathy in connection with the death of your husband Mr. Albert Kahn, who rendered us great service in designing a number of large plants and helped us to assimilate the American experience in the sphere of [the] building industry."
    Kahn's son Edgar's letters to his colleague and mentor Dr. Max M. Peet, in the Neurosurgery Department at the University of Michigan, describe his further medical training in London in 1936 and his military service at Kennedy General Hospital in Memphis, Tennessee, as World War II came to an end. Peet's letters to Edgar in 1942 and 1945 give researchers a view of the changes and challenges at University Hospital during the war years. Letters from other physicians document Edgar Kahn's stature in the field of neurosurgery.
    - Albert Kahn
      - From Albert circa 1896-1942 (Box 1)
      - To Albert 1898-1900 (Box 1)
    - Ernestine Krolik Kahn
      - From Ernestine 1885-1943 (Box 1)
      - To Ernestine 1887-1942 (Box 1)
    - Edgar Adolph Kahn
      - From Edgar circa 1936-1981 (Box 1)
      - To Edgar 1932-1977 (Box 1)
    - Carol Kahn
      - To Carol 1998 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence
      - 1881-1894 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Papers
    The second subseries, Miscellaneous Papers, includes documents which illuminate aspects of family members' professional and personal lives. A Kahn family tree is included to give researchers an understanding of the legacy of Albert and Ernestine Kahn, as well as that of Kahn's brothers and sisters, Julius, Felix, Louis, Gus, Moritz, Mollie and Paula. Ernestine's school certificates document her graduation from Detroit High School in 1887, before she entered the University of Michigan. A small number of newspaper articles about Edgar Kahn illuminates aspects of his hockey prowess at the University of Michigan in the early 1920s, his distinguished military service and his medical career as Chairman of Neurosurgery at University Hospital. Carol Kahn's files of newspaper articles, letters and photographs describe the efforts of a group of citizens to "Save Old Main," University Hospital which Albert Kahn designed and built in 1921. Carol was active in this 1989 preservation campaign which succeeded in saving the entry arch of her grandfather's historic hospital.
    - Kahn Family Tree (Box 1)
    - Ernestine Krolik Kahn's School Certificates 1880-1887 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Articles about Edgar Kahn circa 1921-1960s (Box 1)
    - Program for the Dedication of the William L. Clements Library of American History 6/15/1923 (Box 1)
    - Edgar Kahn's Passport 1929-1933 (Box 1)
    - Edgar Kahn's Congress of Neurosurgery Pendant 1964 (Box 1)
    - Edgar A. Kahn Neurosurgical Meeting Program November 8-9, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Renaming of the New Center Building to the Albert Kahn Building 1988 (Box 1)
    - "Saving Old Main" Campaign 1988-1989
      - "Old Main's Administrative Wing: A Proposal for Preservation" by Nicholas H. Steneck 2/1988 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence File of Carol Kahn 1989 (Box 1)
      - Newspaper Articles 1989 (Box 1)
      - Photographs, circa 1920s, 1989, 37 35 mm. negatives; 1 electrostatic print black and white 8x10-inch (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    The third subseries, Photographs, is arranged chronologically and comprised of images from Ernestine's childhood in the 1870s to her granddaughter Carol Kahn's Ontario canoe trip in 1989. Five photographs depict Albert's and Ernestine's children between 1901 and 1908, and three images show Albert and Ernestine together in their later years. The preponderance of photographs in the collection are of Edgar during his youth, his school years at Andover and the University of Michigan, his European travels, and his medical career in the neurosurgical operating room. These often intimate glimpses of the Kahns in various states of relaxation are significant in providing researchers with a sense of the strong relationships which have bound together the family of the master of American industrial architecture.
    - Ernestine and Joe Krolik circa 1870s, 1 print black and white 2-1/2x4-inch (Box 1)
    - Ernestine Krolik with Others undated, 1 print black and white 1-1/2x3-1/2-inch (Box 1)
    - Albert and Ernestine Kahn's Children 1901-1908, 5 prints of various sizes black and white (Box 1)
    - Edgar Kahn as a Youth circa 1910-1920, 10 prints of various sizes black and white (Box 1)
    - Albert and Ernestine Kahn's Walnut Lake Cottage undated, 1 print black and white 8x10-inch (Box 1)
    - Edgar Kahn's Trip to Bilbao, Spain 1940, 1 pencil caricature 4-1/2x6-inch; 5 and prints black and white 8x10-inch (Box 1)
    - Albert and Ernestine Kahn undated, 2 prints color 5x7 and 2x3 inches (Box 1)
    - Albert Kahn with Airplane undated, 1 print black and white 3-1/2x5-inch (Box 1)
    - Albert Kahn 11/3/1941, 1 copy print; 1 and original black and white 8x10-inch (Box 1)
    - Albert, Ernestine and Edgar Kahn 1942, 1 print black and white 8x10-inch (Box 1)
    - Ernestine Kahn with Edgar, Lydia, Ruth and Rosalie undated, 1 print black and white 8x10-inch (Box 1)
    - Edgar Kahn 1931-1970s, 15 prints of various sizes black and white (Box 1)
    - Carol Kahn Canoeing in Algonquin Park, Ontario circa 1989, 18 35 mm. negatives (Box 1)
    - Unidentified photos undated, 2 prints black and white 2-1/2x3 and 2-1/2x4-1/2 inches (Box 1)
  - Audio Visual Materials
    The Audio-Visual Materials subseries contains one item, an audio tape of an interview, conducted by Carol Kahn with her father, Edgar Kahn, on March 27, 1978.
    - Carol Kahn's interview with Edgar Kahn March 27, 1978, audiotape, 10-inch
- Kahn Family papers, William R. Brashear collector
  Albert Kahn Family Papers received from William R. Brashear consists primarily of papers of his daughter Ruth Kahn Rothman, mainly letters from her husband-to-be William E. Rothman with a scattering of letters from her parents Albert and Ernestine Kahn, some of them written while traveling abroad.
  - Ruth Kahn
    - Letters from Albert and Ernestine Kahn 1923-1929 (Box 1)
    - Letters received from Edward E. Rothman May 1922-1924, 1929, undated, 12 folders (Box 1)
    - Scrapbook / photograph album, Emma Willard School, Troy, New York 1923 (Box 1)
    - Florence, Italy: Photographs and journal entries regarding classes taken and observations 1926 (Box 1)
  - Albert Kahn, letters from Ernestine Kahn and Lydia Kahn written aboard the Mauretania 1923 (Box 1)
  - Lydia Rothman, letters from Albert Kahn 1936, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Edward E. Rothman war-time service (letters from Ruth, typed excerpts from letters home June 1944, describing activities after the D-Day invasion) (Box 1)
  - Albert Kahn newspaper obituaries and other articles about his career (Box 1)
  - Photographs: Edward E. Rothman in uniform, Albert Kahn as part of larger group, and Edward E. Rothman and his six granddaughters (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous: clippings about Eliel Saarinen (Box 1)
Related Material
The Albert Kahn Papers, donated by his firm Albert Kahn Associates, Inc. in 2003, include correspondence, transcripts of speeches, newspaper articles and construction photographs of many of Kahn's most significant buildings. In addition, original, ink-on-linen construction drawings of selected industrial, commercial, institutional and residential projects are part of the Bentley's Albert Kahn collection. The narrative and visual documents in this large collection give researchers the opportunity to study many aspects of the master architect's career and life, from his personal views on industrial architecture contained in his speeches, to the drawings which preserve his icon buildings for posterity on paper. The finding aid for the Albert Kahn Papers is available in hard copy in the reading room of the library and on the Bentley website: http://www.umich.edu/~bhl/EAD/eadlist3.htm